"Is Black Pepper Good for You?"
Black pepper,
the so-called "King of Spices,"
is the most commonly used spice
in the world,
thanks to piperine,
the compound responsible
for black pepper's distinct
biting quality,
as well as some of pepper's
propitious properties,
such as acting as a bioenhancer,
improving the absorption
of other compounds.
Dr. Greger has talked about
how just a tiny pinch
of black pepper--
1/20th of a single teaspoon--
can boost the bioavailability
into the bloodstream
of curcumin, the yellow pigment
of the spice turmeric,
such that
adding turmeric to the diet
with a pinch of pepper
may be more effective
in reducing oxidative stress
and inflammation
than just turmeric alone.
Crack about a quarter teaspoon
of black pepper
onto your vegetables,
and significantly more
carotenoid phytonutrients
will make it
into your bloodstream
than if you ate
the same vegetables without it.
But one of the ways piperine
enhances bioavailability
is by inhibiting
the detox enzymes
in our liver and intestines,
thereby suppressing
our body's ability
to get rid
of foreign substances,
even good ones
like curcumin and beta-carotene.
Could that be a bad thing
for people taking certain drugs?
A systematic review
and meta-analysis
looked at the effects of typical
daily doses of black pepper
on conventional drugs,
and indeed
it increases the bioavailability
of a variety of common ones,
including Dilantin, Inderal,
and an asthma drug
called theophylline.
Now, on the one hand,
that may allow us to give
smaller doses of the drugs,
but on the other hand,
inhibiting
our natural drug detox enzymes
might cause serious consequences
if it led to drug levels
that are too high.
Grapefruit and grapefruit juice
have similar effects,
described as
a "pharmacologist's nightmare,"
which may help explain why those
who increase consumption
by just a half a serving a day
may go on to live shorter lives.
I couldn't find any such study
tracking black pepper
consumption and mortality,
but if you are on medication
and use more than
a pinch of pepper a day,
please tell your prescribing
health professional.